All right, בוקר טוב. boker tov. So today's דף daf is כ"ח,
chaf chet, the beginning of a new פרק, perek, כל האסורין. kol
ha'asurin. This is a significant shift. At the end of last פרק,
perek, we actually finally got to find out
how the act of תמורה temurah is done. Now we turn on
to a very different conversation about what happens in certain cases of
animals getting mixed up with other animals. It's not exactly immediately evident
how this relates to מסכת תמורה, Masechet Temurah, but let's take a
look. Very relevant to other issues. כל האסורין לגבי מזבח. kol ha'asurin
legabei mizbeiach. All animals that are forbidden to be brought to the
altar. I mean, these are issues that we have addressed in this
פרק, perek, things that you cannot bring as a קרבן. korban. We'll
see a list in a minute. Let's say they get mixed up,
one animal that couldn't be brought as a קרבן, korban, for example
we'll see an example that it is let's say a טריפה, tereifah,
and it gets mixed up with a herd of other animals. So
what's the status now? Can you? Even any one of them might
be the טריפה. tereifah. Can you bring it as a קרבן korban
or not? So the משנה mishnah continues to say אוסרין בכל שהוא,
oserin be-chol she-hu,
even in the smallest amount they make the mixture forbidden. So even
if one animal that cannot be brought as a קרבן korban gets
mixed up with a hundred that are totally perfect animals, you cannot
use any of the animals as a קרבן. korban. Okay, so here's
a list of some of those animals that cannot be brought as
a קרבן. korban. הרובע והנרבע, ha'rovei'a ve-hanirva, an animal that was used
in an act of bestiality, whether more the active or passive role.
והמוקצה והנעבד. ha'muktzeh ve-hane'evad. מוקצה muktzeh is not the שבת Shabbat meaning
of מוקצה; muktzeh; it means something that was set aside to be
used for an עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah to be worshipped but never
actually worshipped, or נעבד, ne'evad, thank you, something that was actually worshipped
as an idol. ואתנן ומחיר, ve-etnan u-mechir, something that was, you know,
that's
אתנן etnan is a gift to a prostitute, מחיר mechir is something
that actually was swapped with a dog, מחיר כלב. mechir kelev. All
these things, those are explicit in the תורה, Torah, cannot be used
as a קרבן. korban. והכלאים, ve-hakilayim, a crossbreed, because it's neither a
sheep nor a goat. והטריפה, ve-ha'tereifah, or an animal that is a
טריפה, tereifah, has an inner wound. The גמרא Gemara has a hard
time knowing how would we know it was a טריפה tereifah and
then can't locate it. Talks about a case that has a certain
type of a puncture that based on what caused the puncture would
make it a טריפה tereifah or not and you can now it's
mixed up with other animals that would not that were not problematic.
ויוצא דופן, ve-yotze dofen, or an animal born by Cesarean section. All
of these things we know cannot be brought as a קרבן. korban.
They get mixed up with other animals; none of these animals can
be brought as a קרבן. korban. Now there are different possible scenarios.
This משנה mishnah seems to be talking about that they are all
חולין. chullin. But once they're mixed up, none of them now can
be used. They're all off limits to use as a
קרבן. korban. Wait, if they're all חולין chullin you don't do anything.
You just don't use them as a
קרבן.
korban. Including the one that's חולין? chullin?
You can eat it, you just can't use it as a קרבן.
korban.
No, but what about the טריפה tereifah one?
Oh, okay fine, not a טריפה. tereifah.
You don't know which one it is.
Right. Okay, so then you can't eat all of them. That's טריפה.
treif-ish. You're right. Okay, whether this same הלכה halakhah applies for non-קרבנות
korbanot purposes we'll get to.
That so anyway you can't use them. Another scenario is that they
were all קדשים kodshim and another animal and one animal got mixed
up with it. Right. Then it's not just you can't use them
in קרבן, korban, what do you do with all your קדשים?
kodshim? Mix up their אשמים, ashams, is that what you're saying?
No, I'm saying that you have all these animals that are חטאות
chatos or שלמים shelamim or whatever, and one animal that is a
טריפה tereifah or a רובע או נרבע rovei'a o nirva gets mixed
up. So now none of them can be brought. So what do
you do? You have to let them all graze and get a
blemish and redeem them once they have a blemish and say you
know if this is the one that is that's not the קרבן
korban then forget it, if it is the one that is the
קרבן korban I'm redeeming it. Okay, that discussion when they're already all
קרבנות korbanot and then something that cannot now that is an invalid
one gets mixed up, then that's discussed in the גמרא Gemara in
זבחים. Zevachim. This presumably is the case where they're all חולין. chullin.
But either way the הלכה halakhah is that even the smallest, you
know, proportion, they are all forbidden. Now what is the reason they're
all forbidden? We'll see in the
גמרא. Gemara. It seems from this משנה mishnah and the משנה mishnah
in זבחים Zevachim that something distinctive to the idea that this is
going to be used for קרבנות, korbanot, and therefore that makes it
more severe and we don't allow any concept of ביטול bitul of
nullification. But another possibility has nothing to do with the fact of
קרבנות, korbanot, has to do with the fact that they are בעלי
חיים. ba'alei chayim.
That things that are live animals have are never like you know,
the say, you know, can never sort of lose their identity. Objects
can be somehow can, you know, mixed up with other objects you
know it can somehow be considered it's just an object so you
can say that it like no longer exists, it loses its distinctiveness,
it loses its identity. But live things are always important and even
in a mixture,
you don't know which one it is, but it's never like it
has lost its identity, it's never like it doesn't exist. So we'll
take a look at all of this in the גמרא. Gemara.
But base yeah, shouldn't the רובע rovei'a and נרבע nirva have been
killed right away?
They should have, but say they weren't and before you got a
chance to kill them they got mixed up. So that would be
the scenario. The other issue here is, and that's related to Michael's
question. And that's related to Michael's question about the טריפה, treifa, is
that that, you know, why are these, or that are these things
forbidden because they can't be eaten or they're forbidden in הנאה? hana'ah?
That's one reason to make them forbidden and that's certainly sufficient, and
that's true by the טריפה, treifa, as but the גמרא Gemara also
deals with scenarios where they were not forbidden בהנאה. bahana'ah. Why? Let's
say you didn't have two witnesses to prove that the animal was
a רובע roveia or נרבע. nirba. You'll never wind up killing it.
Or you haven't gotten around to having it have its court case
yet. So it's not yet forbidden in הנאה hana'ah and nevertheless it
still cannot be used as a קרבן. korban. Okay, and we'll see
about that in the גמרא. Gemara.
Wait, I just want to understand.
So let's say you have this מוקצה, muktzeh, right?
And then it's a חולין chulin animal, right? And then it gets
mixed up with all other חולין. chulin. So you have like one
million, you know, your whole flock, and it's mixed in somewhere. So
then basically you don't eat any of them?
You can't use any of them for קרבנות korbanos now. Can you
eat them or whatever? That depends on whether this משנה mishnah is
only true, this idea that it cannot be בטל batel because of
the קרבן korban issue, or would it be true even if it
was just about usability for you to eat it. So we'll take
a look. Our context is only for the fact that you can't
use them as a קרבן. korban.
So then according to what you're saying, you can actually eat it.
We don't mean אסור בכל שהוא assur b'chol she-hu to eat, we
just mean אסור בכל שהוא assur b'chol she-hu as a קרבן למזבח?
korban lamizbe'ach? Correct.
Our משנה, mishnah, the emphasis is that למזבח lamizbe'ach these are all
off-limits. We will talk about whether you can use them when we
get into the גמרא. Gemara. All right, now, המוקצה, hamuktzeh, now אלו
מוקצה, elu muktzeh, what does מוקצה muktzeh mean? המוקצה לעבודת כוכבים הוא
אסור, Hamuktzeh l'avodat kochavim hu assur, something that is set aside for
idolatry, you haven't yet worshipped it but you're planning on it, it
is forbidden. ומשמשיו מותר, U-mash-alo mutar, but however, if you have some
type of a thing that adorns it, that is permissible because we're
going to see in a minute in contrast to the איזהו נעבד,
eizu hu ne'evad, what is something that is worshipped? כל שעובדין אותו,
Kol she-ovdin oso, anything that you worshipped it, okay fine. But the
point is here's the difference: ומשמשיו אסור. u-mash-alo assur. Once you actually
worship an object as an idol, not only is the idol forbidden
but even things that are put on it to adorn it. לא
תחמד כסף וזהב עליהם ולקחת לך. Lo tachmod kesef v'zahav aleihem v'lakachta
lach.
Do not covet the gold and silver that is on them. So
we learn from that that even things that are made to adorn
an idol are also forbidden, but that only is once it is
worshipped. If it is set aside, it does not yet have that
status. It's forbidden, but the objects that adorn it are not forbidden.
וזה וזה מותר באכילה. V'zeh v'zeh mutar b'achila. Now both of these
are permitted in eating. Now what does it mean permitted in eating?
They're עבודה זרה, avoda zara, they're forbidden to be eaten. So the
point is is the following. I mean it's forbidden in benefit. If
it's an animal, it's forbidden to be eaten. So the point here
is, and this is as I pointed out, not, there are case
many of the cases in the משנה mishnah tech- will be ways
in which technically for non-korban purposes they are permitted. They're only forbidden
for קרבן korban purposes. So for example I said that the רובע
roveia and the נרבע nirba could be cases where there aren't two
witnesses or it hasn't yet had the judgment in the בית דין.
beit din. In that case it's not yet forbidden in benefit, but
you still can't use it as a קרבן. korban. For when it
comes to the issue of worshipping an animal as עבודה זרה, avoda
zara, we have a principle that only objects, inanimate objects can be
defined as idols for the sake of being forbidden in הנאה. hana'ah.
Like the גמרא Gemara takes an extreme other example, which is talks
about, you know, it the פסוק pasuk says אלוהיהם על
ההרים, eloheihem al heharim, their gods on the mountains. The mountains can't
become the god. If somebody worshipped the mountain, the whole mountain doesn't
become forbidden in benefit. You cannot make the earth, you know, you
cannot make forbidden in benefit. But the גמרא Gemara goes beyond that
and it's not just that, it's things that are attached to the
ground. Let's say you worship a house. Or it's things that are
even animals, things that are not simple chattel and in- and inanimate
objects. Those are things that can totally be defined through your actions
if it's like a complete it's a complete object. But if it's
something that is part of the earth or it's something that's an
animal that has some independence, then even if you worship it, it
is not forbidden in הנאה. hana'ah. But it is still an object
that was worshipped. So the relevance is, you can eat it, it's
not forbidden in הנאה, hana'ah, but because it is an object that
is worshipped, it cannot be used as a קרבן. korban. And the
things that are on it, because if the things that are on
the animal is not a livestock, is actual and is an inanimate
object, the thing that's on it can genuinely become forbidden in הנאה
hana'ah although the animal itself is not. In a sense it's a
little ironic. The animal is an object that's worshipped and therefore it's
forbidden, it can't be used as a קרבן, korban, but because it's
an animal, it's not forbidden in benefit. The thing that's on it
as a נוי, noy, as a ציפוי, tzipui, as a cover or
adornment for an עבודה זרה, avoda zara, can can become forbidden in
הנאה hana'ah even if the animal is not. We'll talk about that
more in the גמרא. Gemara. Okay, we read this in סנהדרין?
Sanhedrin? Yes, yes.
Now we start right away by comparing this, comparing this משנה mishnah
to a very similar משנה mishnah in זבחים. Zevachim. And in זבחים
Zevachim we have a very similar משנה mishnah that speaks about things
getting mixed up, קרבנות korbanos getting mixed up, and that one of
them is אסור assur and that they all become forbidden. Okay, and
the גמרא Gemara is going to talk about what both what we
are learning differently from each משנה. mishnah. Let's take a look. אמר
מר. Amar mar. ואוסרין בכל שהוא. V'ossrin b'chol she-hu. So according the
משנה mishnah says that they make forbidden even in the smallest proportion,
one in a thousand. דלא בטלי ברובא, De-lo batli b'rubba, that they're
not בטל batel in a majority. Right, these things... remains forbidden. תנינא,
Tanina, but we already taught that in a משנה Mishnah in זבחים.
Zevachim. כל הקדשים שנתערבו בחטאת המתות, Kol hakodashim shenis'arvu b'chatas meisos, או
בשור הנסקל, o b'shor haniskal,
all קרבנות Korbanos that get mixed up in חטאות המתות, chatas meisos,
or שור הנסקל, shor haniskal, an ox that you're going to have
to stone, אפילו אחד בריבו, afillu echad b'ribo,
even one in ten thousand, ימותו, yamusu, they all have to die.
So even the smallest mixture with something that you cannot use as
a קרבן, korban, they all have to die. Those are worse than
not having to use a קרבן, korban, those are things that you
actually would kill. But okay. So the גמרא Gemara says first of
all we have to explain what this משנה Mishnah means, because it
sounds like you're getting one קרבן korban mixed up in a herd
of boring oxen. It says, all sacrifices that are mixed up with
שור הנסקל. shor haniskal. So it sounds like it's one sacrifice mixed
up with a lot of forbidden things. So the גמרא Gemara says
וקשיא לן, v'kashya lan, first of all we ask the question, מאי
קאמר, mai ka'amar, what does this mean? One, of course one קרבן
korban getting mixed up with a hundred not good things is not
good. So הכי קתני, hachi katani, no, no, no, it really means
like the flip. נתערבו בהן מחטאת המתות. Nis'arvu bahen m'chatas meisos.
If you have קרבנות Korbanos and one of a forbidden thing gets
mixed up in them. So we have a thousand קרבנות Korbanos and
one forbidden thing, like a חטאת chatas that has to be put
to death, או שור הנסקל, o b'shor haniskal, or an ox that
has to be stoned, אפילו בריבו, afillu b'ribo, even if it's one
problematic thing getting mixed up in ten thousand קרבנות, Korbanos, ימותו, yamusu,
they all have to be put to death. Okay, so now we
have פשט pshat in that משנה. Mishnah. So both משניות mishnayos are
saying the same thing: one problematic thing getting mixed up in ten
thousand, they're all no good. What, why do we have to teach
it here and also in זבחים? Zevachim? Now, sometimes you could just
say we teach the same thing in multiple places. The גמרא Gemara
said that before, but here we want to point out that each
one is teaching you something slightly different.
There's also a whole list of what these things are. I mean...
Right, okay, but there's a list too. איצטריכא, Itztricha, though it's not
exactly the same. איצטריכא, Itztricha, you need it to tell me in
both places. סלקא דעתך אמינא, Salga daitach amina, I would have thought
to say, התם הוא דאסורי הנאה, hasam hu de'assurei hana'ah, אבל הכא
דלאו אסירי הנאה, aval hacha d'lav assirei hana'ah, אימא לא בטלו בריבו,
eima lo batlu b'ribo, קמשמע לן. kamashma lan. There it's more obvious
that it's a problem. There it talks about a חטאת chatas that
has to die or שור shor that has to be stoned, things
that actually are even for non-קרבן korban purposes cannot be used. If
the ox has to be stoned, it's forbidden for anybody to derive
benefit from. So that's very forbidden. So something that you can't derive
any benefit, that certainly makes the entire herd, even ten thousand of
them, off-limits. Here, it's just a problem for a קרבן. korban. You
know, it's not a problem for normal people. Like we said, you
worship an animal, it doesn't become forbidden for normal people. So maybe
here it's not so bad and maybe here it would be nullified.
So that's why this is a bigger חידוש. chiddush. So the גמרא
Gemara says, okay, but you know what, we've taught that as well.
רבע ונרבע נמי תנינא. Ravav v'nirva nami tanina. Even the case of
animals used in bestiality are mentioned over there in זבחים. Zevachim. It
says the משנה Mishnah continues and says, נתערבו רבע ונרבע, nis'arvu ravav
v'nirva, let them graze till they get a blemish, וימכרו ויביא בדמי
יפה שבהן מאותו המין, v'yimachru v'yavi bidmei yafeh shebahen me'oso hamin, and
you sell, and you buy
from the most expensive one a קרבן, korban, meaning, if you now
have one animal that was used in bestiality mixed up in a
herd, and you don't know which is which, and they range from
value from a hundred dollars per head to a thousand dollars per
head, well, every animal you're redeeming, you don't know whether it is
the קרבן korban or the non-קרבן, korban, so you have to redeem
it at the highest value because it might be what, yeah, because
it might, right, exactly, because you don't know which one is the
קרבן. korban. But anyways, the basic point is you wait for them
to get a blemish and you redeem them. So you see there
you have the same principle of an animal used in bestiality. So
it's exactly what we teach in our משנה. Mishnah. Now, actually, if
there was a rule of בית דין beis din about the, about
these animals, they would also be forbidden בהנאה. be'hana'ah. But the גמרא
Gemara assumes that both here and there that we're talking about there
was not yet a ruling in בית דין beis din and therefore
they are not forbidden to a normal person, they are only forbidden
for the מזבח. mizbei'ach. So it's the exact same הלכה. halacha. Why
do we repeat it in both places?
It was only
based on the שור הנסקל? shor haniskal? Exactly. So why do we
repeat it in both places? So the גמרא Gemara says,
אמר רב כהנא, Amar Rav Kahana, אמריתה לשמעתא קמיה דרב שימי בר
אשי, amrisah l'shema'ata kammai d'Rav Shimi bar Ashi, I said over this
discussion to רב שימי בר אשי, Rav Shimi bar Ashi, ואמר לי,
v'amar li, and he said to me, here's the difference. חדא בחולין
וחדא בקדשים. Chada b'chullin v'chada b'kodashim. Now, that clearly is the difference
by context. There it's explicitly saying that they got mixed up with
קרבנות. Korbanos. Here it is saying that just animals got mixed up.
Okay, they're all non-sanctified yet. So here the point of our משנה
Mishnah is they're all mixed up, you can't use them as קרבנות.
Korbanos. There the point is they're all mixed up and you can't
bring the קרבנות. Korbanos. They are קרבנות, Korbanos, but you can't bring
them because one of them is forbidden. And therefore you have to
wait till it gets a blemish and redeem. That's why this משנה
Mishnah doesn't talk about redeeming and a blemish, because this משנה, Mishnah,
they're not קרבנות Korbanos yet, they're just animals that you otherwise might
have used for them. Okay, and therefore why do you have to
tell me in both cases? Here's why you have to tell me
in both cases. וצריכא, Utzricha, you need to tell me in both
cases. דאי אשמועינן גבי קדשים, De'ee ashmi'inan gabi kodashim,
had you just told me the case by קדשים, kodashim, one problematic
animal gets mixed up with
all... disgusting
that you have these קרבנות korbanot which are already holy and something
problematic got mixed up into it is like, you know, the whole,
the whole herd already is like stigmatized that they've got this thing
mixed up because they already had their קרבן korban status and this
problematic thing entered into the herd. So therefore you can't fix the
problem. אבל גבי חולין אימא ליבטלו. Aval gabei chullin eima libatlu. But
by חולין, chullin, if you fix the problem before you ever sanctified
it, right, they were just animals, nobody was talking about קרבנות, korbanot,
I just had my herd and one, I don't know, one C-section
animal got mixed up, who's even being offended, who's even thinking it's
problematic? So at that stage, right, when you weren't even in the
context of קרבנות, korbanot, you would say fine, it's all nullified. Now
a year later I want to use it as a קרבן, korban,
I can sanctify it, it already took place before it was so
much like it stigmatized the mixture. Okay, this by the way seems
to be pointing to the idea that the reason they're not, that
they're not בטל batel is because it's a particular קרבן korban problem.
For a קרבן korban issue, we cannot gloss over the fact that
there's a problematic animal here. So if that's the issue, that it's
because of the קרבן korban problem, then you could say fine, that's
when the mixture occurred, when they were already קרבנות. korbanot. But maybe
if they weren't קרבנות korbanot yet, maybe we let it be nullified
and later we can use it. So it has to tell me
even in our case, it's a problem even though they're not yet
קרבנות. korbanot.
So the גמרא Gemara says, of course it doesn't tell me why
then if we had our משנה, Mishna, we needed the משנה Mishna
in זבחים. Zevachim. So okay, רש״י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot deal with
that. Part of what the משנה Mishna and we'll see a little
bit more about that in the גמרא. Gemara. Part of what the
משנה Mishna in זבחים Zevachim teaches me is how to fix the
problem. You wait until they blemish and you redeem them. So even
if we could learn from our משנה Mishna it's not בטל, batel,
we learn there how do you fix it if they are קרבנות.
korbanot. But now the גמרא Gemara is not yet done. גמרא Gemara
says like this, ובחולין נמי תנינא, U-v'chullin nami tanina, but we also
taught this by חולין. chullin. What do we teach by חולין? chullin?
That, you know, even by non-קרבנות korbanot there's a problem with mixtures.
Here's what we have in a משנה Mishna in עבודה זרה. Avodah
Zarah. ואלו אסורין ואוסרין בכל שהוא. V'eilu asurin v'osrin b'chol she-hu. The
following things are forbidden even in the smallest amounts in a mixture,
יין נסך, Yayin nesech, wine used in עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah for
libations, not סתם יינם stam yeinam I should mention, which is just
normal wine of a non-Jew which is forbidden, this is specifically used
in idolatrous sort of libations. ועבודה זרה, V'avodah zarah, and things that
are actually worshipped, here we're not talking about animals, this is talking
about just objects, and the common denominator here is that all of
these objects, a lot of them are used in idolatry, but the
real common denominator is that all of them are forbidden in benefit.
And something that is not only forbidden to be eaten, but forbidden
in benefit, is considered to be so problematic that it's not בטל
batel even ברוב, b'rov, even in a mixture, even if there's a
thousand against it, it's never בטל. batel. So you have wine poured
for a libation, עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah, וציפורי
מצורע, V'tziporei metzora, the birds for a מצורע metzora that are, you
know, used in their, in the ritual of the מצורע, metzora, those
are forbidden in benefit. ועורות לבובין, V'orot levuvin, what is an עורות
לבובין? orot levuvin? Basically you see a skin of an animal and
right where the heart is, there is a, there is a, there
is a circle cut out. Okay, sort of like the Indiana Jones
and the Temple of Doom where they grab the heart out from,
so here it doesn't seem like it was for a live animal,
but it does seem that once they, when they would offer certain
animals for certain עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah, they would make a hole
after they slaughtered it, a hole by the heart, and through there
extract all of the internal organs and that would be a particular
idolatrous purpose. So if you find a leather skin like this, you
know it was used as part of an animal that was used
in idolatry.
ושער נזיר, U-se'ar nazir, excuse me, ושער נזיר, v'se'ar nazir, the hair
of a נזיר nazir is forbidden in benefit, you're supposed to burn
it in the fire when you cook the meat of one of
the קרבנות. korbanot. ופטר חמור, U-petter chamor, the firstborn of the donkey
which is forbidden in הנאה, hana'ah, you do not redeem it.
ובשר בחלב, U-basar b'chalav, meat and milk that were cooked together. Now
that does not mean, yes it is, it does not mean a
drop of milk fell into your chicken soup. Then it is not
yet meat and milk. Then it is meat and milk, so the
meat, the milk is בטל batel in the meat if it's less
than a 60th. But once you create בשר בחלב, basar b'chalav, you
actually cooked meat and milk together and then this got mixed up,
this thing that was cooked with cheese, this burger gets mixed up
with a thousand burgers that were not cooked with cheese, or a
tiny drop of it goes into some vegetable soup or whatever. There,
even a thousand times is not בטל batel when it already has
become בשר בחלב. basar b'chalav. Okay,
ושור הנסקל, V'shor haniskal, and an ox that has to be stoned.
ועגלה ערופה, Va-eglah arufah, and a, the calf that you break the
neck when you don't know who the murderer is. וחולין שנשחטו בעזרה,
V'chullin she-nishchetu b'azarah, or חולין chullin that were slaughtered in the בית
המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, that also is forbidden הנאה. hana'ah. ושעיר המשתלח, V'sa'ir
hamishtaleach, or the goat that was sent away on יום כיפור. Yom
Kippur. All of these things are forbidden הנאה. hana'ah. Interesting because why
this list is coming up, it doesn't mention
חמץ. chametz. I don't know the question about the
גירסא. girsa. Anyway, הרי אלו אסורין. harei eilu asurin. different set of
things is a problem. There what the problem is things that are
forbidden in benefit. In our משנה, mishna, it is things that are
distinctive קרבן korban problems which we learn from other verses, right? I
mean, for God's sake, a C-section animal. So the גמרא Gemara says,
so that's what the גמרא Gemara says. It says צריכא, tzricha, no
you need both. And again, it's a little funny because that sounds
like they're mostly redundant. They're not mostly redundant. They're very different. Anyway,
דאישמעינן התם, de'ashmi'inan hasam, had it just said there, now we're going
to do with the גירסא girsa actually in our text which is
actually the הגר"א HaGra says is the right גירסא, girsa, not the
way it was fixed on the side. If it had just told
us over there דאיסורי הנאה לא בטילי, de'issurei hana'ah lo boteili, that's
because they're forbidden in benefit. That's the reason that they're forbidden and
therefore even for non-קרבן korban purposes. אבל הכא ליבטל, aval hacha libatel,
but here maybe it should be בטל. batel. Here these things are
not forbidden in benefit. C-section,
crossbreed, right? Who would say this is a problem?
ואישמעינן הכא, v'ashmi'inan hacha, had it just told us here לגבוה, legavoah,
maybe that's a unique קרבן korban problem דמאיס d'me'is because that's disgusting.
אבל להדיוט, aval le'hedyot, but for a non-קרבן korban purpose, אימא איסורי
הנאה ליבטלו ברובא, eima issurei hana'ah libatlu b'ruba, maybe even
things that are forbidden in benefit should be nullified. קמשמע לן kamashma
lan no. So what is the upshot of all of this? The
upshot of all of this is, if you take the simple message
of our גמרא, Gemara, that when it comes to non-קרבן korban purposes,
for normal lay purposes, a person can I eat it, can I
benefit from it, the only thing that is not בטל, batel, or
well there's a lot of different laws of ביטול, bitul, but the
only thing that's not בטל batel at all, even in ten thousand,
even the tiniest amount, are things that are forbidden בהנאה. be'hana'ah. That
seems to be the rule here. When it comes to קרבנות, korbanos,
whatever can't be used as a קרבן, korban, right? Even pretty innocuous
things like C-section animals and crossbred animals and whatever, but because it's
specifically about קרבנות, korbanos, when they get mixed up, even whether they
get mixed up before it became a קרבן, korban, like it's in
all, just your normal herd, or it gets mixed up with קרבנות,
korbanos, when it specifically comes to קרבן korban also you do not
have the rules of ביטול bitul and you can't use any of
them and if they're קרבנות korbanos you have to redeem them. So
those seem to be what are the two principles. I should say
though, mentioning that, that number one the גמרא Gemara in זבחים Zevachim
actually, you know, sort of as the discussion develops there, points out
that in most of the cases here by the קרבנות, korbanos, even
if it weren't the קרבן korban issue, it would be בטל batel
for the reason that I said, which is that if it's a
live animal, then it is not, live animals are not בטל. batel.
And that is true even in sort of like non-קרבן korban purposes.
So what's maybe unique about קרבן korban is after you שחט shacht
ed it. Because for example if it's really true that live things
are not בטל, batel, well let me just move past that. Okay,
so live things are not בטל batel and we actually do say
that even for non-קרבן korban purposes. So for a lot of this
it's even not the, although here it sounds like it's distinctive because
it's קרבנות, korbanos, in the גמרא Gemara in זבחים Zevachim they actually
say that for many, for most of these cases you don't even
need that because the thing just by being live is significant enough
not to be בטל. batel. In terms of the other issue that
איסורי הנאה issurei hana'ah are not בטל, batel, there's another גמרא Gemara
in עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah or whatever that mentions other criteria as
well. So just to let you be aware that the impression you
get here is not the end of the story. The way it's
being framed here is there's two things that are never בטל. batel.
Things that are forbidden as קרבנות, korbanos, for קרבן korban purposes they're
never בטל, batel, okay? And therefore if that mixture, whether they get
mixed up with חולין, chullin, mixed up with קרבנות, korbanos, never בטל.
batel. And things that are אסור בהנאה asur be'hana'ah when they get
mixed up are never בטל batel even for lay purposes. That's the
basic rule. But again גמרא, Gemara, other גמרות gemaros introduce other factors,
for example the fact that livestock is never בטל batel maybe even
for non-קרבן korban purposes.
Yeah, isn't there a גמרא Gemara there, like even רב אלעזר, Rav
Elazar, like says that
let's say you already offered one of them, you can offer all
the rest of them because you can say that was the one
that was...
Yeah, so that's right, that's the גמרא Gemara in זבחים. Zevachim. Let's
not worry about that either, but correct. Okay, so now the גמרא.
Gemara. So we have these rules of things that are not בטל
batel and for us the rule is when it comes to קרבן
korban purposes, if you can't use it as a קרבן, korban, even
one in ten thousand gets mixed up, you can't use any of
them. Now we're going to discuss where we know these things cannot
be used as a קרבן. korban. Let's take a look. רובע ונרבע
מנלן דפסולי לגבוה? Roveia v'nirva minalan d'psuli legavoah?
How do I know that things used in bestiality cannot be used
for, for a קרבן? korban? Now again, this means before it actually
had the ruling in the בית דין beis din that said that
it would have to be, you know, that it would have to
be stoned. Once that's true, if it's even as a להדיוט le'hedyot
you can't benefit from it, then you obviously can't use it as
a קרבן. korban. We're going to see later a principle that says
that anything that a lay person cannot eat or benefit from cannot
be used as a קרבן. korban. But we are talking here that
it has not had that ruling in בית דין, beis din, so
therefore the question is and nevertheless it is forbidden. The owner knows,
we know that it did it, but maybe there were not two
witnesses and you can't use it as a קרבן. korban. So let's
take a look where. How do we know that they're forbidden for
קרבנות? korbanot? דתנו רבנן, detanu rabbanan, מן הבהמה, min habehema, it says,
you
know, it says אדם כי יקריב מכם קרבן לה', Adam ki yakriv
mikem korban la'Hashem, if you bring
a קרבן, korban, מן הבהמה מן הבקר
ומן הצאן תקריבו את קרבנכם, min habehema min habakar umin hatzon takrivu
es korbanchem,
from the animals, from the, you know, from the cattle or from
the sheep you should bring your קרבן. korban. So the גמרא Gemara
assumes that a lot of those words are extra. Okay, certainly the
fact that it says מן הבהמה, min habehema, from the בהמה, behema,
which means you can't use all animals, only a subset. מן הבהמה
להוציא רובע ונרבע, min habehema lehotzi roveia venirba,
to exclude animals used in bestiality. So the גמרא Gemara says: ולא
דינו? velo dino? One minute, it's a, I could have known, who
needs a פסוק? pasuk? I could have learned it out logically. How
could I have learned it out logically? Or even by a קל
וחומר. kal vachomer. ומה בעל מום שלא נעבדה בו עבירה פסול לגבי
מזבח, umah baal mum shelo neevda bo aveira pasul legabei mizbeiach, if
an animal with a blemish, which doesn't even have, you know, as
it would, hasn't even had a sin done to it, it's only
a physical blemish, as it were, it's not a moral or religious
blemish, it's only a physical blemish, you can't use it for the
altar. רובע
ונרבע שנעבדה בהם עבירה אינו דין שיאסר לגבי מזבח? roveia venirba shene'evda
bahem aveira einu din sheyeaser legabei mizbeiach?
How much more should they be forbidden? So Michael doesn't buy it,
neither does the גמרא, Gemara, but let's take a look. The גמרא
Gemara so, it continues, says, you know what? That would not have
proven it. First of all, I could have a counter-example. What's my
counter-example? חורש בשור וחמור יוכיח. choresh b'shor v'chamor yochiach. If I used
animals in, in a כלאים, kilayim, again, not to create a crossbreed,
but I, you know, I had them work together, an ox and
a donkey. We learn from another place that you can still use
the ox for a קרבן, korban, even though it was used in
a sin. Okay, שנעבדה בו עבירה ומותר לגבי מזבח, shene'evda bo aveira
umutar legabei mizbeiach, you can use it as a קרבן. korban. Says,
no, I, that's not a proof, a counterproof. מה לחורש בשור וחמור
שאין חייב מיתה? mah l'choresh b'shor v'chamor sheein chayav misa? That's not
a counterproof, because those things, the sin is not so terrible that
the, that you know, that there's a death penalty on you and
on the animal. But in an act of bestiality where there's a
death penalty on you and on the animal, that is such a
weighty sin that of course that should be forbidden, that should be
forbidden to the altar. So the גמרא Gemara says: תאמר ברובע ונרבע
שחייב מיתה? tomar beroveia venirba shechayav misa? How about those? So the
גמרא Gemara says: alright, טול לך מה שהבאת. tol lach mah sheheiveisa.
הרי שנעבדה בהן עבירה בשני עדים. harei shene'evda bahen aveira bishnei eidin.
Fine. So then, fine, so you, you can prove the case where
actually there is going to be a death penalty, that the act
was done in front of witnesses and there will be a death
penalty. That I'll grant you. Fine. That you know can't be used
for the altar, can't be used for etc., for other reasons as
well. But nevertheless, על פי עד אחד או על פי בעלים מנלן?
al pi eid echad o al pi baalim minalan? How about if
you don't have two witnesses? How about if just one witness, how
about the owner's admission that this is how it was used? How
do you know that when it's not a death penalty on the
animal, the very fact that the sin was done is enough to
say that it cannot be used as, as a sacrifice? And maybe
that's why you need a פסוק pasuk because you would not have
been able to learn that out on your own. So let's take
a look. So the גמרא Gemara says, where do you know it?
אמר רב שימי: Amar Rav Shimi: אני דן, ani dan, I will
figure it out from, just by logic without a פסוק. pasuk. ומה
בעל מום שאין הסרת שניים פסלת מאכילה הודאת עד אחד פסלת מהקרבה.
umah baal mum sheein hasara shnayim pasalta meachila hodaas eid echad pasalta
mehakrava. Again, from a קל וחומר. kal vachomer. It's true that you
might not have two witnesses, but it's a type of thing that
if you did have two witnesses would be disastrous. So when it
comes to a בעל מום, baal mum, two witnesses could say it's
a blemish, it's still going to be permissible for a layperson. And
nevertheless, when one person says it's a blemish or whatever, it's going
to be forbidden. So that's true by an animal with a blemish.
רובע ונרבע שהסרת שניים פסלת מאכילה. roveia venirba shehasara shnayim pasalta meachila.
By a case of an animal used in bestiality, if you did
have two witnesses, this thing would really be, would be forbidden even
for a layperson, would be forbidden to eat. So therefore, אינו דין
שהודאת עד אחד פסלת מהקרבה? einu din shehodaas eid echad pasalta mehakrava?
Even if you don't have two witnesses, even if you only have
one witness, it's obviously, it's the type of thing was done to
it that is serious enough that it could make it forbidden in
eating if you had that type of testimony. So even without that
testimony, that should be weighty enough to say it can't be used
as a קרבן. korban. So we could have used it, learned it
out logically. Who needed a פסוק? pasuk? תלמוד לומר, talmud lomar, but,
no, we have a פסוק: pasuk: מן הבהמה להוציא רובע ונרבע, min
habehema lehotzi roveia venirba, from the animals to exclude רובע ונרבע. roveia
venirba. So the גמרא Gemara says: ויכתוב פסוק? הא אתיא מדינא. vayichtov
pasuk? ha atiya midinya. Didn't you just get through saying you could
learn it out logically? So the גמרא Gemara says: no, not necessarily.
אמר רב אשי, amar Rav Ashi, משום דאיכא למימר, mishum deika lmeimar,
Rav Ashi says, because you could say: מעיקרא דינך פירכא. meikara dinach
pircha. You could challenge the קל וחומר kal vachomer from its very
root. And what could you have said? This is probably what Michael
was thinking. מה לבעל מום שכן מומו ניכר. mah lbaal mum sheken
mumu nikar. Okay, you know, there's idea of certain being morally blemished
and about being physically blemished, but sometimes aesthetics matters more. You know,
if it's a בעל מום, baal mum, so it's evident, you can
see the problem, that maybe is more problematic than some type of...
something where it's invisible and it's just about its past history. טמא
ברובע ואין בשמיה מום ניכר. Tamei berova ve'ein bishmiya mum nikar. How
about this animal who's used bestiality? It's not visible and therefore maybe
that's not a problem, maybe specifically the problem is aesthetics and what's
visible and not this type of a thing. So how would you
know therefore that that's a problem? תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, so therefore
the verse teaches מן הבהמה min habehema להוציא רובע ונרבע. lehotzi rova
venirva. So that's how we know to exclude bestiality. So the purpose
of this little exercise is not just to point out why you
needed a פסוק, pasuk, but also to point out like where this
fits in the constellation, like in the logical, sort of structure about
why things are forbidden. So on the one hand there is a
compelling logic that it is forbidden because it is a type of
a, whether sort of moral religious blemish on the animal, but nevertheless,
you could not have proven that by yourself because it is a
different quality than a physical blemish and that's what the פסוק pasuk
teaches. So that's how we know those are forbidden. מן הבקר, Min
habakar, now we keep on going from all these extra מן, min,
from means not all. So from cattle להוציא הנעבד, lehotzi hane'evad, an
animal that was worshipped. Okay, again, you don't have witness here even
if you know that it was worshipped with witnesses or whatever, the
animal is not forbidden in benefit as I said before, only inanimate
objects become idols, not livestock. They do not become forbidden in benefit,
but they are forbidden to the altar. ולא דין הוא? Velo din
hu? One minute, it's a קל וחומר. kal vachomer. ומה אתנן ומחיר
שציפוייהן מותרין Uma etnan umechira shetzipuyehen mutarin הן אסורין, hen asurin, when
you deal with something like a אתנן ומחיר, etnan umechira, gift to
a prostitute or an animal exchange or female prostitute or animal exchange
with a dog, those types of things, those are forbidden to the
altar, that's what the one really explicit פסוק, pasuk, that don't bring
them as קרבן. korban. Nevertheless there is no concept by them of
adornments. Right? The whole הלכה halacha we mentioned before when you worship
an animal even the adornments on it are forbidden. Okay, so there
those are forbidden to the altar even though there's no concept of
adornments and if you had something to adorn them it would not
be problematic. נעבד שציפוייו אסורין, Ne'evad shetzipuyav asurin, an object that is
worshipped that we know that its adornments are forbidden, not even to
the altar, are forbidden for a normal person. אינו דין שהוא אסור,
Eino din shehu asur, how much more so should it itself be
forbidden on the altar? So that, why, why do you need a
פסוק? pasuk? You could have made a קל וחומר. kal vachomer. Wait
a minute, the גמרא Gemara says או חילוף, o chiluf, no, here's
why you needed a פסוק. pasuk. Because you could have said the
exact, you could have learned out the exact reverse. You could have
said the following. If I didn't have a פסוק, pasuk, I would
have started by assuming an object worshipped, an animal worshipped, because it
doesn't become forbidden in benefit, an animal worshipped is permissible as a
קרבן korban if I didn't have a פסוק. pasuk. And then I
would have made the קל וחומר kal vachomer the opposite way and
I would have said ומה אתנן ומחיר שהן אסורין uma etnan umechira
shehen asurin and nevertheless ציפוייהן מותרין, tzipuyehen mutarin, their adornments are permissible
for benefit and for קרבנות, korbanot, there's no concept of adornment of
them. נעבד שמותר, Ne'evad shemutar, so if the animal that's worshipped if
I didn't have a פסוק pasuk I would have said I could
bring it as a קרבן korban and then I would have made
a קל וחומר kal vachomer יהיו ציפויו מותרין, yihiyu tzipuyav mutarin, how
much more so would the adornments be permissible? Okay, so that's why
I need a פסוק pasuk cause if I didn't have a פסוק
pasuk I would have said it's permissible, you want to make a
קל וחומר kal vachomer tell me it's אסור? asur? No, I'll make
a קל וחומר kal vachomer the opposite way to tell me that
there's no concept of problematic adornments. So the גמרא Gemara doesn't have
a פסוק pasuk to back it up, either one? Ah, well that's
what the גמרא Gemara is about to say. גמרא Gemara says no,
no, no, you could never have said there that the adornments were
permissible. אם כן ביטלת לא תחמוד כסף וזהב עליהם ולקחת לך. Im
ken bitalta lo tachmod kesef vezahav aleihem velakachta lach. The פסוק pasuk
we know that the adornments are forbidden, it says don't covet the
gold and silver on the idols and take it for you. So
you so you would never have been able to have made the
opposite argument. So if we know that the adornments are forbidden and
you can't change that fact, it'll allow us to make a קל
וחומר kal vachomer that the objects themselves are forbidden for a קרבן.
korban. גמרא Gemara says no, אני מקיימנו, ani mekayamnu, I could have
dealt with the פסוק. pasuk. I could have said לא תחמוד כסף
וזהב, lo tachmod kesef vezahav, when are adornments forbidden? בדבר שאין בו
רוח חיים, bedavar she'ein bo ruach chayim, if it's an inanimate object,
if the object itself is forbidden in benefit, the adornments are forbidden
in benefit. אבל בדבר שיש בו רוח חיים, Aval bidavar sheyesh bo
ruach chayim, if the animal, if it's a live thing, then therefore
it itself is not forbidden for lay purposes and if it's not
forbidden for lay purposes cause it's a live thing, הואיל והן מותרין
ho'il vehen mutarin since the animals are permitted, יכול יהיו ציפויין מותרין,
yachol yihiyu tzipuyun mutarin, I could have said that the adornments are
permissible. So if I had not had a פסוק pasuk to tell
me don't bring this worship animal as a קרבן, korban, on the
one hand I could have started with the assumption that you can't
use the adornments and
made a קל וחומר kal vachomer from אתנן ומחיר etnan umechira to
say it's forbidden in a קרבן, korban, or I could have said
no, maybe who knows about the adornments? Maybe that prohibition is only
when the object is an inanimate object and I could have said
the קל וחומר kal vachomer the opposite way. Without a פסוק, pasuk,
maybe it's permissible as a קרבן korban and not only that, if
it's permissible as a קרבן korban then there's no problem with the
adornments either, like an אתנן etnan and a מחיר. mechira. Because if
I hadn't had a פסוק, pasuk, then why would I have thought
that a worship No פסוק, pasuk, and it's permissible in benefit because
it's a live thing. Live things do not become אסור assur in
forbidden in benefit as a worshiped thing. So this is pointing out
why I needed a פסוק. pasuk. The whole thing is, oh who
needs a פסוק, pasuk, I can learn it out from something else?
Learn it out from אתנן esnan and מחיר. mechir. So the Gemara
says, no, without a פסוק pasuk I would have said that—learn out
from אתנן esnan and מחיר mechir the opposite way. Without a פסוק
pasuk I would say it's permissible, and not only that, its adornments
are permissible, קל וחומר kal vachomer from אתנן esnan and מחיר. mechir.
So that's why I need a פסוק. pasuk. תלמוד לומר, talmud lomar,
the verse teaches, מן הבקר min habakar להוציא את הנעבד. lehotzi et
hane'evad. That's why I needed a פסוק, pasuk, because since I could
not have known to start with the problem of the adornments, that
would have been up for grabs, so therefore the פסוק pasuk has
to teach—I couldn't have learned it out from אתנן esnan and מחיר,
mechir, and the פסוק pasuk has to tell me that even that—you
cannot bring an object worshipped, an animal worshipped, even though it does
not become forbidden in benefit. So the end of the day is,
by the way, it's not exactly clear what the מסקנא maskana is,
but רש״י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot both insist that the הלכה halacha
is that when it—it is a little ironic, but that when you
worship an animal, although the animal itself is not forbidden in benefit,
it's forbidden as a קרבן korban but not from benefit, if it
has things that adorn it, those things are forbidden that are inanimate,
those things are forbidden in benefit. Okay, it's not like the animal
is not labeled as an עבודה זרה. avoda zara. The proof that
it is labeled as an עבודה זרה avoda zara is you can't
use it as a קרבן. korban. It's just that because it is
a live thing, it does not become forbidden in benefit, that's a
special הלכה, halacha, but that therefore—but that would not extend to the
things on it, the things on it would be considered adornments of
עבודה זרה avoda zara and forbidden in benefit. Michael, you have a
question. Yeah, so if regarding the אתנן זונה, esnan zona, so which
is אסור, assur, so let's say it was an אתנן קדש, esnan
kadesh, it would be מותר? mutar? Yeah, the זונה zona is only
an הלכה halacha of אתנן זונה. esnan zona. Right, would you say
that זונה zona is just paradigmatic, it's most common? No, the גמרא
Gemara interprets that פסוק pasuk very, very narrowly, very specifically. That's very
interesting. So what—so just zeroing in, so essentially... Yeah, I mean here
we're not—the גמרא Gemara is not analyzing אתנן esnan and מחיר, mechir,
but the... what? Sure. Yeah, also pretty—yeah, extremely narrowly defined, right. You
can still say that, you know, some thing if it was prostitute,
it's just prostitute. Right. It says female. Michael, it's in the next
משנה, mishna, so it's tomorrow's דף. daf. Okay, you can raise all
those questions. Are those forbidden in benefit? What? No, those are only
קרבנות, korbanot,
and that was the... just like the animal that was worshipped as
עבודה זרה. avoda zara. Right. Okay, so we're going to have a
lot of fun here. This entire פרק, perek, כל האסורין, Kol Haasurin,
is all about what types of things are forbidden as a קרבן.
korban. Okay, again, what exactly it's doing in תמורה, Temurah, not exactly
clear, maybe because we dealt a lot with the חטאות המתות, chatot
hametot, but okay, we will see. Anyway, let's take a look. So
now it goes on. Okay, so now we know one פסוק pasuk
to forbid רובע ונרבע, rove'a v'nirba, bestiality, one פסוק pasuk used for
עבודה זרה. avoda zara. Now the גמרא Gemara says like this. מתיב
רב חנינא, metiv Rav Chanina, טעמא דמיעט קרא, taama demiat kra, the
reason is you got a—you have a פסוק. pasuk. הא לא מיעט
קרא ציפויו מותר. ha lo miat kra tzipuyo mutar. You were arguing
that without a פסוק pasuk to know that this was אסור assur
as a קרבן, korban, you could have come to the conclusion that
the adornments are permissible. And you would have said the problem of
adornments are only when
you have an inanimate object that's your idol. Since that then is
forbidden, the adornments are forbidden. So how could you have come to
that conclusion? והכתיב, vehaktiv, the verse says, ואבדתם את שמם, v'ibadetem et
shemam, you should—thank you, ואבדתם, v'ibadetem, you should destroy their name, their
memory. כל העשוי לשמם, kol ha'asuy lishmam, anything made for, you know,
for the sake of עבודה זרה avoda zara has to be destroyed.
So that seems to be very categorical and should have, you know,
should have applied even to things that were adornments for animals. How
could you have said that, suggested that those things would not have
been forbidden? The גמרא Gemara says: No, that פסוק pasuk would not
have necessarily applied that way. I would have said the פסוק pasuk
means something very different. ההוא, hahu, what would I have done with
that פסוק? pasuk? לכנות להם שם, l'chanot lahem shem, it tells me
literally their name, שמם, shemam, that you should make a—use some different
word to refer to עבודה זרה, avoda zara, and you should not
keep their names, the names of the עבודה זרה avoda zara should
not sort of—should lose their currency, should, you know, be forgotten. What
does this mean?
And now we're not just saying don't use the names, but I
mean, look, everybody knows right that there's these long-standing, you know, Jewish
practices, you know, not to refer to Christian things exactly. You know,
there's I told you this, there's we once actually had a whole
question about אלהים אחרים לא תזכירו. elohim acherim lo tazkiru. But you
know, I mean but it's not only about saying the names of,
you know, but and you know, there's a funny story that once
in הרב סולובייצ'יק's Harav Soloveitchik שיעור, shiur, somebody was saying something to
him: "You know, יש״ו, Yeshu, אותו האיש," oto ha'ish, everybody was saying
like... And the Rav says, "What do you mean, Jesus?" So... but
you know, but Jews will say things like כרזמא? Chrasma? Right? They
won't say things that are like names of עבודה זרה avoda zara
types of things. You know, that's within a separate conversation about Christianity,
you know, and so on, and how that is or is not
over time defined or not defined as עבודה זרה. avoda zara. But
anyway. But we all know those like internalized things about sort of
the way things are referred to. So here the גמרא Gemara gets
to that, but it's not only just sort of come up with
another name, like by the way, you know, but it's actually coming
up with a derogatory name. Actually, there's a word for this. It's
as opposed to euphemism, which is a nicer name for something, I
forget, there actually is a word that means a like a derogatory,
like changing the name for something that is actually a way of
putting something down. It's not euphemism, but it's the opposite. Somebody look
that up. What? Look up in some antonym dictionary you'll find there's
an opposite to the word euphemism. Anyway, so the גמרא Gemara says
like this, so for example, the בית גליא Beis Galya which was
the name of a certain house of עבודה זרה, avoda zara, and
גל gal means some like a high place, like a mound, a
high place, קרינן ליה karinan lei בית כריא. Beis Karya. You call
it בית כריא. Beis Karya. רש"י Rashi wants, here's רש"י Rashi בית
כליא, Beis Kalya, which means place of destruction or he says the
place of like a hole, a hole in the ground which is
like a latrine. Okay, פני המולך, Pnei haMolech, the face of Molech.
It's interesting in the context of saying what, you know, that you
shouldn't be saying these names, you say okay, fine, right, anyway. So
מולך Molech was and also has a context of המולך. haMolech. I
know, I know. That has like a מלך, melech, right? But מולך
Molech was also the name of the god. פני כלב, Pnei Kelev,
so the face of a dog. עין כל, Ein Kol, which is
the name of some place, presumably some, either, probably not the name
of an עבודה זרה avoda zara but a place of idolatry, which
then the eye of all, like everybody is looking on it or
it looks upon everything, instead you call it עין קוץ, Ein Kotz,
a thorn in the eye. And so actually sometimes it is interesting
to find, you know, in writing, particularly in the Middle Ages, creative
ways in which they came up with these anti-euphemisms for for things
related to other religions. Like one thing was, oh yeah, very creative
one. When they wanted to refer to a church, instead of calling
it a בית תפילה, Beis Tefilla, a house of prayer, they call
it בית תיפלה. Beis Tifla. Right. Because תיפלה tifla means like, you
know, nonsense, תיפלות tiflus or whatever. So, or when instead when they
wanted to talk of the study halls, rather than calling it a
בית המדרש, Beis haMidrash, they would call it a בית המדרס. Beis
haMidras. Because מדרס midras is like a seat of like a זב
zav or a נדה, niddah, you know, or you know, whatever, which
basically is something about, you know, that you that becomes something that
becomes טמא. tamei. Anyway, so look, I mean, it's you know, not
exactly something to valorize here. We live in a much more, you
know, tolerant and pluralistic, you know, society, but we also have to
appreciate that, you know, a certain degree of universalism and pluralism and
tolerance is a luxury. It's because we are we're treated as equal
and that we have it so well. When you are an oppressed
people, to be able to give a little sense of, you know,
protecting your own value, you know, as opposed to the much more
dominant and oppressive, you know, you know, other nations, you understand sometimes,
you know, the serious need, psychological need for this type of for
this for this term. Some of the names of the days of
our week or the months, right? Haven't those been a big problem?
That is an excellent point. Not only that, I mean, we just
got through reading the מגילה, Megilla, the names of the Persian gods,
but besides that, right, the whole מגילה Megilla when it says כי
עת, Ki Es, כי הפור הוא הגורל, Ki haPur hu haGoral, אסתר
הדסה היא אסתר. Esther Hadassah hi Esther. What it's doing is it's
translating Persian names with Hebrew names. But also it does it for
the month names. בחודש הראשון הוא חודש ניסן. Bachodesh harishon hu chodesh
Nissan. Why? Because חודש הראשון chodesh harishon is the Hebrew name. ניסן
Nissan is the Persian name. All of our names of the month
are Persian names and the Persian names are named mostly after Persian
gods. Okay, and you can find this out on the go to
Wikipedia, whatever, you look it up, you'll find it out all there.
So it's a real problem. So the same way we have a
problem with Sunday and Monday, Sun's Day, Moon's Day, right? Whatever, Saturday,
Saturn's Day, right? They already started a good, you know, fifteen hundred,
or whatever, twenty-five hundred years ago, you know, with the names of
the months. So the רמב"ן Ramban tries to explain why we do
that because he's got another problem because החודש הזה לכם ראש חודשים
Hachodesh hazeh lachem rosh chodashim is a מצוה. mitzvah. And he says
the מצוה mitzvah is to count the months by their number in
order to make ניסן Nissan the first, in order to remember יציאת
מצרים. Yetzias Mitzrayim. So how do we replace it with Persian names
that we whatever happened to this מצוה mitzvah of counting the month
like חודש ראשון חודש שני. chodesh rishon chodesh sheni. So he says,
well, because by remember using the Persian names, we remember the second
redemption from בבל Bavel when we came back to build the בית
המקדש Beis haMikdash the second time. You know, maybe that's what we
remember, maybe actually it's just a sign of assimilation. So it is
a real question, you know, why we do that, and if you
want to be פרום, frum, you won't do that, you'll say חודש
ראשון chodesh rishon and יום ראשון yom rishon and you won't, there
are people that are very מחמיר machmir on that.
Okay, yeah, shorthand in your cell 1/1/21. You don't count that either?
No,
we don't count the month of January's not. Yeah, okay, but that's
not a problem about השמעת שמי, hashma’as shemi, that's just a problem
about החודש הזה לכם. Hachodesh hazeh lachem. Okay. Also used euphemisms. Wait,
but what's the opposite of euphemism? Dysphemism. Dysphemism, thank you. Like a
dystopia, like a utopia and a dystopia. Okay, dysphemism. D-Y-S. Okay. All
right, very good. So anyways, that's what I would have done with
the פסוק, pasuk, not to tell me things about ornaments, and now
we're back to where we were. That's why I might have thought
the ornaments of live animals that were worshipped were okay. And now
that I have a פסוק pasuk to tell me you don't use
the animal for a קרבן, korban, I know also that the ornaments
are forbidden. Okay, now the גמרא gemara goes on and says the
following.
Now the גמרא gemara says like: ואיפכא אנא. ve'eipak ana. Why do
I learn רובע ונרבע roveia venirva from מן הבהמה min habehemah and
a worship thing from מן הבקר? min habakar? Why don't I flip
which I learn from which word? Is it arbitrary? Is there a
reason? I learn one from one word and the other from the
other? So the גמרא gemara says: No. מן הבהמה להוציא את הנרבע
ומן הבקר... min habehemah lehotzi es hanerva u'min habakar... why don't I
flip it and say מן הבהמה להוציא את הנרבע ומן הבקר להוציא
רובע ונרבע? min habehemah lehotzi es hanerva u'min habakar lehotzi roveia venirva?
The answer is התם מעניינא דקרא והכא מעניינא דקרא. hasam me'inyana de'kra
vehacha me'inyana de'kra. You know, in each place, it's the context of
the word suggests this idea. How do you know? כתיב גבי בהמה
kesiv gabei behemah because we have by הבהמה, habehemah, what does the
פסוק pasuk say? ואיש כי יתן שכבתו בבהמה מות יומת. v'ish ki
yitein shechovto b'behemah mos yumos. The פסוק pasuk that prohibits, one of
the פסוקים pesukim that prohibits bestiality, says if a person lies with
a בהמה. behemah. So if I'm going to exclude something from מן
הבהמה, min habehemah, it's going to be an animal used in bestiality.
That's, you know, the word is associated with that. מות יומת. mos
yumos. גבי בקר כתיב, gabei bakar kesiv, now by the word בקר,
bakar, cattle, it says: וימירו את כבודם בתבנית שור vayamiru es kevodam
b'savnis shor אוכל עשב. ochel esev. They exchanged right there their glory,
God, by the image of an ox, you know, eating grass. So
there it specifically is about cattle, you know, so it talks about
the עגל הזהב. eigel hazahav. Anyway, cattle is specifically associated with עבודה
זרה avoda zara and therefore בקר bakar is to exclude עבודה זרה.
avoda zara. Okay, now, so now we've excluded רובע ונרבע ונעבד. roveia
venirva vene'evad. Now we keep on going. מן הצאן, min hatzon, from
the sheep, not all the sheep, להוציא את המוקצה lehotzi es hamuktza
to exclude an animal that was designated to be worshipped even if
it has yet to be worshipped. ומן הצאן, u'min hatzon, the extra
ו, vav, and from the צאן, tzon, another thing we're excluding, להוציא
את הנוגח lehotzi es hanogei'ach a שור shor that has gored. Again,
even if it has not yet a שור הנסקל, shor haniskal, hasn't
had a ruling of בית דין, beis din, if it has gored
and killed somebody, it cannot be.
Three... Being two totally different things from like, you know, essentially the
same word?
Yeah, that's true. אמר רבי שמעון, amar rabbi shimon, אם נאמר רובע
למה נאמר נוגח אם נאמר נוגח למה נאמר רובע? im ne'emar roveia
lamah ne'emar nogei'ach im ne'emar nogei'ach lamah ne'emar roveia? Why do I
need both? Like both of them basically did something, you know, did
a sin, although one a human did a sin with it. And
both of them if you have a בית דין beis din will
be put to death. So why can't I just learn one from
the other? לפי שיש ברובע מה שאין בנוגח ויש בנוגח מה שאין
ברובע. lefi sheyesh baroveia mah she'ein benogei'ach v'yesh benogei'ach mah she'ein baroveia.
Each of them has distinctive qualities. What are the distinctive qualities? יש
ברובע שהרובע עושה אונס כרצון. yesh baroveia sheharoveia oseh ones k'ratzon. By
a case of רובע, roveia, it's even if the animal is not
a willful participant, right? If a person forces himself on an animal,
not a willful participant, you'd still put the animal to death. But
you might have thought that there is, so on the one hand,
you would have said it's not as bad, it wasn't willful. But
on the other, no, no, no, if the תורה torah is demanding
it be put to death even if it's not willful, then that's
a very weighty judgment on it, you know, and therefore the prohibition
is considered
weightier, too. So maybe only that would have been forbidden because even
an אונס ones gets to this status. מה שאין בנוגח. mah she'ein
benogei'ach. It's not true by an animal that gores. If an animal
is fixed on somebody, the גמרא gemara talks about stadium animals, right,
in the context of Rome, and if basically you took an animal
and you sort of incited it to kill someone, the animal would
not be a שור הנסקל, shor haniskal, would not be considered a
נוגח, nogei'ach, only if it did it on its own, not if
it was incited by a human. So therefore right, so therefore that
might have been lighter because it's only willful. And on the other
hand, יש בנוגח, yesh benogei'ach, there's something about a goring animal that
is weightier. What is that? שהנוגח משלם את הכופר. shenogei'ach meshaleim es
hakofer. If an animal gores and it does it three times, then
the owner has to pay כופר, kofer, right, this atonement price, because
the owner was negligent in the death of others. That is something
you only find by a goring animal, a killing animal, you do
not find by רובע ונרבע. roveia venirva. מה שאין ברובע, mah she'ein
baroveia, you don't have by רובע, roveia, obviously because a רובע roveia
didn't kill anybody. Anyway, therefore they each have distinctive qualities. Yeah, I
understand that. Like fine. הוצרך לומר רובע והוצרך לומר נוגח. hutzrach lomar
roveia vehutzrach lomar nogei'ach. Because they're not exactly the same, you needed
both. Fine. So therefore that's how we get them all out: מן
הבקר מן הבהמה מן הצאן, min habakar min habehemah min hatzon, you
get out everything pretty much everything on the list. Not everything, you
have the case of crossbreed, יוצא דופן, yotzei dofen, that we've learned
out from elsewhere. But the new things we've introduced, those you learn
out from this פסוק. pasuk. So now the גמרא gemara goes on
and says והאי תנא מהיכא מייתי לה מהכא, ve'hai tana meiheicha maisi
lah me'hacha, והאי תנא מהיכא מייתי לה מהכא. ve'hai tana meiheicha maisi
lah me'hacha. That's where one תנא tana learns it out from, that
whole פסוק. pasuk. But we have another ברייתא, braisa, another תנא, tana,
that learns these things out from a different
פסוק. pasuk. דתניא, detanya, ותנא ברייתא. v'tanah baraisa. הרובע והנרבע. haroveia vehanirva.
So this says וכולם, v'chulam, but the שיח יצחק Siyach Itzhak is
a גרסא girsa to וכולי, v'chulei, which means etcetera. etc., okay, which
is the rest of this, this whole list of things that are
forbidden, הם כקדשים שקדם מום עובר להקדשן, hem ke-kodshim she-kadma mum over
le-hekdeshan, they are like an animal that the blemish preceded them being
sanctified, so if you sanctify them they never get a קדושת הגוף,
kedushat ha-guf, they never get a sanctity for the altar, right, they
only get a sanctity for the value, but it compares it actually
to a transitory blemish. Why does it compare it to a transitory
blemish? Because you cannot redeem them without a blemish. Remember we had
that whole discussion about if an animal's the wrong gender, is that
so removed from the category that it doesn't need a blemish? So
here too, although these things are forbidden, because it's not a blemish,
וצריכי מום קבוע לפדות עליהן, u-tzrikhei mum kavua lifdos aleihen, you actually
need them to get a blemish in order to redeem them. Okay,
that was fascinating, that wasn't exactly our topic, but that's important that
these things need a blemish to be redeemed even though they're forbidden.
Meaning you've sanctified it after it was רובע ונרבע rovia ve-nirva then
you sanctified it. Right. And you don't say it was nothing, but
rather you need it you need to redeem the money for like
you know the עולה olah or whatever, exactly.
Okay, so now, so that's a separate point which is introducing a
new point. And now it says שנאמר she-ne'emar as the verse tells
us, כי משחתם בהם מום בם, ki moshchasam ba-hem mum bam, because
their corruption is in them, their blemish is in them. So מאי
תלמודא mai talmuda what is that פסוק pasuk telling me about this
idea that you need a blemish to redeem it? So אמר Amar
מר Mar חסורי מחסרא והכי קתני. chasorei me-chasra ve-hakhi kasani. No, no,
it's missing some words here's what it's saying. This פסוק pasuk is
not proving the last point about the need of the blemish to
redeem, it's proving the basic point about how you know they're forbidden.
מניין שהן אסורין, Minayin she-hen asurin, how do I know that these
things are forbidden? תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, כי משחתם בהם מום בם.
ki moshchasam ba-hem mum bam. So their the corruption is in them,
their blemish is in them. Now the simple sense of that פסוק
pasuk was talking about a physical blemish. How do I know to
apply it to these things? ותנא דבי רבי ישמעאל Ve-tanna devei Rabbi
Yishmael we taught in the house of Rabbi Yishmael, כל מקום שנאמר
השחתה אינו אלא דבר ערוה ועבודת כוכבים. kol makom she-ne'emar hashchasah eino
ela devar ervah ve-avodas kokhavim. When it talks about corruption it refers
to idolatry and and sexual sin. דבר ערוה Devar ervah דכתיב di-khasiv
sexual sin because כי השחית כל בשר דרכו על הארץ, ki hishchis
kol basar darko al ha-aretz, all flesh had corrupted its way. Now
it's not explicit in the פסוק pasuk but of course the general
understanding of חז"ל Chazal probably also because of the word כל בשר
kol basar flesh has to do with sexual sin,
a sort of a moral corruption. ועבודת כוכבים Ve-avodas kokhavim דכתיב di-khasiv
פן תשחיתון ועשיתם לכם פסל תמונת כל סמל, pen tishchisun va-asitem lakhem
pesel temunas kol samel, lest you act corruptly and you make for
yourself an image. So therefore because it is corrupting the idea of
God. So this idea that says a מום mum is based on
השחתה hashchasah is tells you the עבודה זרה avodah zarah issues and
the רובע ונרבע, rovia ve-nirva, it doesn't tell you the נוגח. nogei'ach.
It's interesting, right? Those are the big three: עבודה זרה, גילוי עריות,
שפיכות דמים, avodah zarah, gillui arayot, shefikhut damim, right? So if you
think about it, right, those are the three we're dealing with here:
idolatry, sexual sin, and murder. It does not actually mention the נוגח.
nogei'ach. Our משנה mishnah did not mention נוגח. nogei'ach. So maybe he
would learn it from somewhere else. Maybe he would say, maybe he
would try to, you know, find a way to say השחתה hashchasah
also includes the idea of נוגח. nogei'ach. But what
is fascinating here is that it goes back, it echoes back the
earlier point. And by not learning it from a פסוק pasuk of
מן הבהמה מן הבקר ומן הצאן min ha-behemah min ha-bakar u-min ha-tzon
and learning it instead from this פסוק pasuk of משחתם בהם, moshchasam
ba-hem, it's really saying that at a conceptual level this is like
a moral religious blemish, right? It's conceptually like a מום, mum, it's
not a physical blemish, it's a different type of a blemish. It's
a moral, it's an ethical, it's a religious blemish and that's what
it is. Okay, so that's I think an interesting conceptual way of
framing it which you really get from this. Nevertheless you still need
a physical blemish to redeem it. So that conceptual framing doesn't exactly
change the הלכה, halakhah, but it is an interesting conceptual framing. So
now that we have another פסוק, pasuk, the גמרא Gemara just wants
to know, okay, so what do you do with everybody with the
other person's פסוק? pasuk? So let's take a look.
Okay, ותנא דבי רבי ישמעאל מן הבהמה מן הבקר ומן הצאן מאי
דרש ביה? Ve-tanna devei Rabbi Yishmael min ha-behemah min ha-bakar u-min ha-tzon
mai darish beih? What does he, if you learn it from this
פסוק pasuk about this blemish, this religious blemish, what do you do
with the פסוק pasuk about מן הבהמה מן הבקר ומן הצאן? min
ha-behemah min ha-bakar u-min ha-tzon? What do you learn from that? מאי
דרש ביה? mai darish beih? מיבעי ליה mibai lei פרט לחולה ולזקן
ולמזוהם. perat le-choleh u-le-zaken u-le-mezuham. Things that are also physically offensive or
disgusting but are don't exactly have a blemish. An animal that's like,
you know, very old and about to collapse, or an animal that
is sick, or an animal that is smelly. These types of things
are similar, if you would, aesthetic problems without technically being a blemish.
Those are also excluded and we learn that from this פסוק.
pasuk. ותנא קמא Ve-tanna kamma דאפיק להו
להני קראי לרובע ונרבע, de-appik le-hu le-hanei kra'ei le-rovia ve-nirva, the תנא
קמא tanna kamma that used those earlier פסוקים pesukim for all for
all of the first
things, חולה וזקן ומזוהם choleh ve-zaken u-mezuham מנא ליה? mena leh? How
does he know to exclude this new category of things that are
smelly and, you know, whatever, sickly and so on? נפקא ליה Nafka
leh מן הצאן מן הכבשים ומן העזים. min ha-tzon min ha-kevasim u-min
ha-izzim. Because when the תורה Torah goes on, it says if you
bring
your your קרבן korban from the from the flock, it can be
from the sheep or from the goats. So there's a couple more
מןs, min from, from, from. So those extra מןs min mean not
all of them to exclude these things. ולתנא דבי רבי ישמעאל, u-le-tanna
devei Rabbi Yishmael, what does the תנא דבי ישמעאל, tanna devei Yishmael,
what does he do with all those extra
Of course if that's the way the פסוק *pasuk* talks, what about
המן הבקר ומן הצאן *ha-min habakar u'min hatzon*? So the גמרא *Gemara*
says the first פסוק *pasuk* was really
extra, because
why does it have to say מן הבהמה מן הבקר ומן הצאן
*min hab'hemah min habakar u'min hatzon*? Why didn't it just say right
away, if you bring it from the בקר *bakar* here's the הלכה
*halacha*, if you bring it from the צאן *tzon* here's the הלכה
*halacha*? So that was really extra. But here already דיברה תורה כלשון
בני אדם *dibra Torah kilshon bnei adam*, we don't learn anything special
from it. And we will continue.